Finding aid for the Sylvia Plath collection MRBC.MS.00045
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Sylvia Plath collection
approximately 1930-1998
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Plath, Sylvia
MRBC.MS.00045
26.75 linear feet (55 boxes, 4 items, and 2 flat file folders)
The Sylvia Plath collection contains writings by and about the American poet, novelist, and Smith College graduate, including poems, journals, articles, and correspondence to and from Plath. The bulk of the collection is manuscript, printed, or published materials but also includes realia, and audio/visual materials.
Scope and Contents
The Sylvia Plath Collection contains writings by and about Sylvia Plath, including poems, journals, articles, and correspondence to and from Plath. The bulk of the collection is manuscript, printed, or published materials but also includes realia, and audio/visual materials. There are also personal and financial papers, photographs, artwork, and school papers. While the bulk of the collection is comprised of Sylvia Plath's writings, memorabilia, and reviews of her work, there are also materials concerning Aurelia Plath (Sylvia Plath's mother), Otto Plath (Sylvia Plath's father), Ted Hughes (Sylvia Plath's husband), Olwyn Hughes (Ted Hughes' sister), and Marcia Brown Stern (friend of Sylvia Plath). These additional series are largely comprised of materials relating to Sylvia Plath. The Ted Hughes materials contain some of his own writings and correspondence in addition to documents concerning his publication of Sylvia Plath's works.
Related Materials
While the Sylvia Plath Collection is the largest collection of Plath materials at Smith College, there are other collections for researchers to consult at Smith and elsewhere such as the collections listed below.
Jane Anderson papers
Edward Butscher papers
Helle collection of Plath family photographs
Steinberg, Peter. Steinberg photographs of Sylvia Plath related places
Peter K. Steinberg. Collection of newspaper articles relating to Sylvia Plath's suicide attempt, 1953
Houghton Mifflin Company. Collection of papers about "Bitter Fame"
Other resources at Smith relating to Sylvia Plath can be found in the Smith College Archives and Printed books by and about Sylvia Plath are cataloged and accessible through the Five-College online catalog. Other major collections are held at the Lilly Library at Indiana University and Emory University Special Collections holds the Ted Hughes Papers.
Biographical / Historical
The American poet and novelist Sylvia Plath was born on 27 October 1932 in Boston, Massachusetts, to Otto and Aurelia Schober Plath. After graduating from Smith College in 1955, she attended Newnham College at Cambridge University on a Fulbright fellowship.
Plath married British poet Ted Hughes on 16 June 1956. The couple moved to Massachusetts after Plath graduated from Cambridge. Plath was an English instructor at Smith College from 1957 to 1958 while her husband taught English literature and creative writing at the University of Massachusetts at the Amherst campus before they moved to Boston to write for a year.
In 1959, Plath audited Robert Lowell's poetry writing course at Boston University where she met the poet Anne Sexton. After a ten-week stay at Yaddo, the artist's colony in Saratoga Springs, New York, the couple moved back to England in December.
Heinemann published Plath's first book, The Colossus: Poems, in London in 1960; The Bell Jar, Plath's thinly disguised autobiographical novel, was published by Heinemann three years later in 1963.
Plath died from suicide on 11 February 1963. Her Ariel poems were published posthumously by Faber and Faber in 1965, and her Collected Poems (1981) won the Pulitzer Prize in 1982.
Chronology of major events in Sylvia Plath's life, 1932-1963
1932 October 27—Sylvia Plath born in Boston, Massachusetts, to Otto and Aurelia Schober Plath.
1935 April 27—Warren Joseph Plath (Sylvia's brother) is born.
1936 The Plath family moves from Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts, to Winthrop, Massachusetts, to be close to Aurelia Plath's parents.
1940 November 5—Otto Plath dies from complications of diabetes.
1941 Aurelia and her children and parents move to Wellesley, Massachusetts.
1944 September—Sylvia enters Phillips Junior High School.
1947 June—Sylvia graduates from Phillips Junior High School. September—Sylvia enters Gamaliel Bradford High School.
1950 June—Sylvia graduates from Gamaliel Bradford High School. September—Sylvia enters Smith College and lives in Haven House (September 1950-June 1952) and Lawrence House (September 1952-June 1955).
1953 June—Sylvia spends the summer in New York as guest editor of Mademoiselle. August 24—Sylvia attempts to commit suicide by taking an overdose of sleeping pills. October—Sylvia moves to McLean Hospital, a private psychiatric facility in Belmont, Massachusetts.
1954 February—Sylvia returns to Smith College.
1955 May—Sylvia is awarded a Fulbright fellowship to Newnham College, Cambridge. June 6—Sylvia graduates summa cum laude from Smith College with an honors degree in English. October—Sylvia enrolls at Newnham College, Cambridge. She lives at Whitstead, a house for foreign students.
1956 February 25—Sylvia meets Ted Hughes.
1956 June 16—Ted and Sylvia are married at the Church of St. George the Martyr, London. June-August—Ted and Sylvia travel through Spain. September—Sylvia and Ted visit the Hughes family in Yorkshire. October—Sylvia returns to Cambridge. Ted returns to London. December—Ted and Sylvia move to 55 Eltisley Avenue, Cambridge.
1957 June—Sylvia completes her B.A. degree at Cambridge. June—Sylvia and Ted sail to New York. They visit Wellesley and spend the summer on Cape Cod. September—Sylvia begins teaching English at Smith College. She and Ted live at 337 Elm Street in Northampton, Massachusetts.
1958 September—Sylvia and Ted move to an apartment at 9 Willow Street in Boston, Massachusetts. Sylvia works part-time as a secretary at Massachusetts General Hospital's adult psychiatric clinic.
1959 Spring—Sylvia works at Harvard University in the Sanskrit and Indian Studies department and audits Robert Lowell's writing of poetry course (English 306) at Boston University. Summer—Sylvia and Ted drive across Canada and the United States to visit Sylvia's aunt Frieda Plath Heinrichs and her husband Walter J. Henrichs in California. September-November—Sylvia and Ted are guests at Yaddo, an artists' colony in Saratoga Springs, New York. December—Sylvia and Ted move back to England.
1960 Sylvia and Ted rent an apartment at 3 Chalcot Square in London. April 1—Sylvia gives birth to a daughter, Frieda Rebecca Hughes. October 31 —The Colossus and Other Poems is published in London.
1961 August—Sylvia and Ted move to Court Green, their home in North Tawton, Devonshire.
1962 January 17—Sylvia gives birth to a son, Nicholas Farrar Hughes. October—Sylvia and Ted separate. December—Sylvia and the children move to 23 Fitzroy Road, London.
1963 January 14—The Bell Jar is published in London under the pseudonym Victoria Lucas. February 11—Sylvia dies from suicide in her home in London.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was purchased from the Estate of Sylvia Plath in 1981. Aurelia Plath, Sylvia's mother, donated additional material in 1983. The rest of the collection was donated or sold to Smith College by friends of Sylvia Plath, including Ann Davidow Goodman, Elinor Friedman Klein, Enid Epstein Mark, and Marcia Brown Stern, and by booksellers. Whenever the provenance of particular items are known, this is noted in the description.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Women poets--20th century; Women poets, American; Women novelists, American; Plath, Sylvia; Hughes, Ted, 1930-1998; Hughes, Olwyn; Plath, Aurelia Schober; Plath, Otto Emil, 1885-1940; Stern, Marcia Brown, Class of 1954; Stern, Marcia Brown, Class of 1954
- Writings, 1949-1963; 1; 9.3 linear feet (17 boxes; 8 oversize folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains manuscript, typescript, and published writings by Sylvia Plath including articles, broadcast transcripts, journals, poems, short stories, and reviews.
  Arrangement
  Sylvia Plath's writings are arranged into subseries by genre and alphabetically by title within each genre.
  - Articles, 1950-1963; 1; .625 linear feet (1 box; 1 oversize folder)
    This subseries contains published articles from magazines and newspapers, annotated by Sylvia Plath or Aurelia Plath and one typescript of "Tea with Olive Higgins Prouty."
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "America! America!", 1963 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Printed version from Punch, volume 244, pages 482-84.
    - "As a Baby-Sitter Sees It", 1951 November 6-7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor, in two parts, with illustrations of children by Sylvia Plath.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Aurelia S. Plath, 12/03/1983.
    - "Austrian-Born Junior Enlists in Marine Corps, 'Can't Wait to Get There'", 1953 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Printed version from Daily Hampshire Gazette, page 2, four copies.
    - "Cambridge Vistas", 1958 December (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Printed version from Institute of International Education News Bulletin, pages 22-28, with extra clipping of illustration by Sylvia Plath, byline has married name.
    - "In Retrospect: A Plea for Moderation" and part of "A Tigress Special! being A Critical Evaluation of the Modes and Habits of the modern College Man", 1951 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 4.1)
      "In Retrospect: A Plea for Moderation" by Sylvia Plath and Marcia Brown: printed version in The Princeton Tiger, pages 14-15.
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Second copy (Gift of Aurelia S. Plath, 12/03/1983) in Series 17 Writing, Artwork & Memorabilia of Others: Box 42, Folder 2).
    - "John Mason Brown Lectures on Writer's Responsibility", 1953 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 4.2)
      Printed version from Daily Hampshire Gazette, Northampton, page 18. Written by Sylvia Plath about a lecture at Smith College.
    - "Kitchen of the Fig Tree", 1959 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor, page 8, with illustrations by Sylvia Plath (two copies).
      Second copy was a gift of Aurelia S. Plath, 12/03/1983
    - "Laughton Holds Audience Spellbound with Readings", 1953 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Printed version from Daily Hampshire Gazette, signed with initials Sylvia Plath.
    - "Leaves from a Cambridge Notebook", 1956 March 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor in two parts. The first part includes illustration by Sylvia Plath.
    - "Mlle's last word on college, '53", 1953 August (Box 43, Folder 3)
      Pprinted version in Mademoiselle, page 235. Features an image of Sylvia Plath and other Mademoiselle guest editors in a star formation, along with Sylvia Plath's's text.
    - "The Neilson Professor", Fall 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7.1)
      Printed version in Smith Alumnae Quarterly, page 12. From the library of Sylvia Plath, with her signature on the cover. The cover also annotated by Aurelia Plath.
    - "Poets on campus: five talented young men combine poetry and the classroom", 1953 August (Box 43, Folder 3)
      Printed version in Mademoiselle, pages 290-91.
    - "Rewards of a New England Summer", 1950 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor.
    - "Shale That Is 400,000,000 Years Old at Smith Lab", 1953 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Printed version from Daily Hampshire Gazette with copy of typescript from Smith College Archives.
      Printed version, Gift of Aurelia S. Plath, 12/03/1983.
    - "Sketchbook of a Spanish Summer", 1956 November 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor, in two parts, with illustrations by Sylvia Plath.
    - "Smith College Play Delights 'Hamp Audience", 1953 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Printed version from The Springfield Union, page 31.
    - " 'Smith Review' Revived" and "Sketches of the Pulitzer Prize winners in journalism, letters and music for 1955" (Box 1, Folder 11.1)
      " 'Smith Review' Revived" printed version in Smith Alumnae Quarterly, page 26, 1953 fall. Annotated by Aurelia Plath. Laid in: newspaper clipping, "Sketches of the Pulitzer Prize winners in journalism, letters and music for 1955," The New York Times, page C28, 1955 May 3.
    - Typescript of "Tea with Olive Higgins Prouty" and rejection letter from The Reader's Digest, 1955 July 19; undated; 7 Leaves (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "A Walk to Withens", 1959 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor, page 12.
    - "Youth's Plea for World Peace", 1950-03-16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Printed version from The Christian Science Monitor of "Youth's Plea for World Peace" by Sylvia Plath and Perry Norton, page 19.
  - Broadcasts, 1961-1963; 2; .2 linear feet (4 folders)
    The subseries, Broadcasts, contains several BBC typescripts, annotated and corrected by Plath as well as others, for various programs.
    The typescripts are arranged alphabetically by the name of the program, and the dates listed are the broadcast dates.
    - Radio Times listings including listings for "Poets in Partnership", 1961 January 26; 1961 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Full page and clipping of Radio Times listings for the braodcast "Poets in Partnership: Ted Hughes and Sylvia Plath discuss with Owen Leeming what it is being married to the Muse as well as to each other."
    - BBC typescript of "The Living Poet" with annotations by Sylvia Plath and Anthony Thwaite, 1961 July 8; 9 Leaves (Box 1, Folder 15.1)
      BBC Third Programme broadcast in which the following poems were read by Sylvia Plath and Marvin Kane: "The Disquieting Muses," "Sleep in the Mojave Desert," "Suicide Off Egg Rock," "Spinster," "Parliament Hill Fields," "You're," "Magi," "Medallion," "The Stones [Poem for a Birthday: 7]." With: clipping of BBC Third Programme listing for this broadcast.
    - BBC typescript for "New Comment" with corrections by Sylvia Plath, 1963 January 10; 7 Leaves (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Live BBC Third Programme broadcast in which Sylvia Plath reviewed Donald Hall's anthology "Contemporary American Poetry."
    - "The World of Books" typescripts, 1962 July 7; 6 Leaves (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Carbon typescript and BBC typescript for "The World of Books," BBC Home Service broadcast on the poet versus the novelist. Both are corrected by Sylvia Plath and are three leaves each. The carbon typescript is titled "A Comparison."
  - Journals, 1950-1962; 3; .66 linear feet (2 boxes)
    All of Plath's journals in this collection are printed in The Journals of Sylvia Plath 1950-1962 (London: Faber and Faber, 2000; published as The Unabridged Journals of Sylvia Plath, New York: Anchor Books, 2000), edited by Karen V. Kukil. These editions include an extensive index.
    This subseries is comprised of manuscript and typescript journals of Sylvia Plath.
    Journals are arranged chronologically. Since Plath kept simultaneous journals, there is some overlap.
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1950 July through 1953 July; 432 pages 432 numbered pages (pages 421-32 blank); Autograph manuscript on lined paper, bound in three-quarter red and black cloth ledger binding, gold-stamped on spine: LAW/NOTES/6-L/COOP. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1951 October 17-19; 4 Leaves 4 unnumbered leaves (6 pages); Autograph manuscript on lined notebook paper (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1953 January 18; 1 Leaves 1 leaf (2 pages); Autograph manuscript list on yellow paper. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1953 March 24; 1 Leaves; Typescript on paper torn from pocket notebook. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1953 April 5; 1 Leaves; Typescript on paper torn from pocket notebook. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1953 April 9; 1 Leaves; Typescript on paper torn from pocket notebook. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1953 June 19; 1 Leaves; Typescript on verso of yellow Street & Smith Publications memorandum paper. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1953 June-July; 3 Leaves (3 unnumbered leaves); Typescript journal. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1955 November-1956 April; 38 Leaves (38 numbered leaves); Typescript on white paper with autograph manuscript corrections. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1955 December 31-1956 January 1; 5 Leaves (5 numbered leaves); Typescript on lined paper (torn from a two-hole notebook) with autograph manuscript corrections. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1956 March 26-April 5; 24 Leaves (24 numbered leaves); Typescript on lined paper (torn from a two-hole notebook) with autograph manuscript corrections. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1956 April 1; 1 pages; Autograph manuscript on lined paper, torn from a two-hole notebook. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1956 April 16; 1 pages; Autograph manuscript on lined paper, torn from a two-hole notebook. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1956 June-1961 March; 68 Leaves (Leaves are numbered, many missing); Autograph manuscript in Challenge Duplicate Book. Includes 4 pages of drawings. With a photocopy of "Miss Drake Proceeds to Supper." Also includes a photocopy of a drawing of Ted Hughes, previously separated and not owned by Smith College Special Collections. (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Separated Materials
      "Miss Drake Proceeds to Supper" (page 14) moved to Poems (Box 11, Folder 159, item 1).
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original is fragile, use photocopy first.
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1956 July 15; 5 Leaves (5 numbered leaves); Typescript on white paper with autograph manuscript corrections. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1956 July 22-August 26; 18 Leaves (18 numbered leaves, many leaves are missing); Typescript with autograph manuscript corrections, pages probably torn from a Challenge Triplicate Book. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1957 January 3-March 11; 10 Leaves; Typescript on white paper with autograph manuscript corrections. Most pages are headed "Cambridge Diary." (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1957 June-1960 June; 20 Leaves ([20] numbered leaves, many leaves are missing.); Autograph manuscript, pages probably torn from a Challenge Triplicate Book and include two drawings including the "corn-girl" vase. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1957 July 15-August 21; 10 Leaves ([10] leaves); Typescript on white paper with autograph manuscript corrections and underlining. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1957 August 28-1958 October 15; 181 pages 181, [3] numbered pages (pages 177-78 are lacking); Autograph manuscript on lined paper, half-bound in red cloth with maroon paper over boards, blind-stamped on back cover: C. Cambridge Ltd. / Birmingham / C.B. 900, iv. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1957 October 1; 4 pages (4 numbered pages); Typescript on white paper with autograph manuscript corrections. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1957 November 5; 2 Leaves (2 numbered leaves); Typescript on white paper with autograph manuscript corrections. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Hospital notes", 1958; 5 Leaves (5 numbered leaves); "Hospital notes" typescript on verso of pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Sylvia Plath journal, 1958 December 12-1959 November 15; 71 Leaves; Typescript on verso of pink Smith College memorandum paper with autograph manuscript corrections, annotations, and drawings. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "Notes on Neighbors", 1962; 34 pages 34 unnumbered pages (5 blank); Typescript on lined legal-size paper with autograph manuscript corrections (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Novels, 1961-1971; 4; .8 linear feet (2 boxes)
    Photocopy and orginal pages of drafts of the novels of Sylvia Plath as well as notes, correspondence and clilppings concerning The Bell Jar, Doubletake, and Falcon Yard. There are no complete drafts in this collection. The drafts of The Bell Jar identified here as Early, Second, and Third were written on the reverse of drafts of various poems. The original pages are filed under the appropriate poem and photocopies are supplied here.
    - Holograph outline of The Bell Jar chapters, approximately spring 1961; 1 Leaves (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Holograph outline of chapters from The Bell Jar, one page, on Smith College memorandum paper. On reverse: typescript draft of The Bell Jar, page 14, with autograph annotations and corrections by Sylvia Plath.
    - Photocopies of The Bell Jar early draft, not before 1961; 43 pages (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Photocopies of early draft typescripts for The Bell Jar. Typescript is one-and-a-half spaced, with Sylvia Plath's corrections. Chapter number and page number typed or written at top of page in Sylvia Plath's hand.
    - Photocopies of The Bell Jar second draft, 89 pages (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Photocopies of second draft typescripts of The Bell Jar with Sylvia Plath's corrections and computations. "SECOND DRAFT. Chapters 1-16" written by Sylvia Plath at head of first page. Chapter number and page number typed or written at top of each page in Sylvia Plath's hand. On first page, title is changed from "Diary of a Suicide" to "The Bell Jar," and author is changed from "Frieda Lucas" to "Victoria Lucas." Changed throughout: "Janeen" to "Doreen"; "Frieda" to "Victoria".
    - Photocopies of The Bell Jar third draft, 17 pages (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Photocopies of The Bell Jar third draft typescript double-spaced, with Sylvia Plath's corrections. "THE BELL JAR", "Plath", and consecutive page numbers typed at top of each page.
    - Typescript of The Bell Jar later draft, approximately 1961; 264 pages ([3], 264 pages) (Box 4, Folder 5-24)
      Later draft typescript of The Bell Jar with corrections and revisions by Sylvia Plath, as well as alterations made by James Michie, at her request, and the copy editor. Preliminary pages typed by Heinemann.
      Each chapter (1-20) is in a separate folder.
    - Holograph notes on textual changes to The Bell Jar later draft, undated; 3 pages (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Holograph notes on textual changes to The Bell Jar later draft. On reverse: "Venus in the Seventh", typescript (page 25), a chapter from Sylvia Plath's novel "Falcon Yard", undated.
    - Carbon typescript of The Bell Jar later draft, approximately 1961; 264 pages (Box 5, Folder 26-45)
      Later draft carbon typescript of The Bell Jar with some corrections and revisions by Sylvia Plath.
    - Photocopy of typescript letter from Eugene F. Saxton Memorial Trust to Sylvia Plath, 1961 November 6 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      Typed letter (signed) to Sylvia Plath from the secretary of the Eugene F. Saxton Memorial Trust, announcing the award of a Saxton grant to Sylvia Plath, 1961 Nov 6.
    - Photocopy of typed letter from Sylvia Plath to James Michie, 1961 November 14; 2 pages (Box 5, Folder 46)
      Typed letter from Sylvia Plath to James Michie, her editor.
    - Photocopy of New York Times article concerning the Eugene F. Saxton Memorial Trust fellowship award to Sylvia Plath, 1961 November 21 (Box 5, Folder 46.1)